Hopefully that's everybody on Zoom
connected. Okay. And also everybody
locally. All right. Today we're going to
continue talking about Marov decision
processes. Let's recap what that is. And
then today is going to be a deep dive
into something called the Bellman
equations which are basically the heart
of everything that happens not only in
MDPs for non-deterministic search but
also for reinforcement learning.
Starting next lecture, we'll be getting
into reinforcement learning and we'll
see a little hint of what that's about
and what the key ideas are towards the
end of today.
All right, so let's recap our running
example of Markov decision process,
which is this world grid world. We also
saw another one about a car racing and
overheating. Um, grid world is a
maze-like problem. You live at an x y
coordinate on a grid. There are walls
that block your path. There are pits you
can fall into and gems that you can take
as prizes. The actions are north, south,
east, and west. And in certain squares,
the action exit. Um, 80% of the time the
action north actually takes you north.
10% of the time it takes you west
instead. 10% of the time east and you're
always have this chance symmetrically of
going in either direction 90 degrees
from what you intended. That amount,
that exact percent is the noise. And
it's a parameter we can change to
illustrate different environments. Okay,
it's not part of the solution. It's part
of the environment. Some environments
are noisy, some are not. If there's a
wall in the direction, then you stay
put. And that gives rise to some of the
weird corner cases like walking into a
wall intentionally so that you can slide
left and right without risking going
backwards. Um, in terms of rewards,
there is there are rewards here, the
plus one and the minus one that are
shown on the grid in the visualizations.
And there's also an invisible uh in the
visualization but still present living
reward which is something you receive
every single step. This is in contrast
with the games that we were doing
minimax on where you play chess and
there is no reward until the end when
you win or lose here the rewards trickle
in. And in general that's actually very
important. One because you got to keep
track of that stuff in the algorithms.
And two because when we talk about
discounting discounting future rewards
it means not only are the rewards not
all at the end but the rewards at the
end may be so heavily discounted that
they don't matter. And it's that balance
between what rewards you get and when
you get them that drives behavior. The
goal in grid world is to maximize the
sum of your rewards or if we put a
discount on it, the sum of discounted
rewards. To remind ourselves what an MDP
is, anytime you see MDP, you should
think non-deterministic search. That's
all it is. It's states and actions. It's
just those actions have probabilistic
outcomes. So just like search, just like
things we've been talking about since
the beginning of the semester, there's a
set of states S. Usually it's
combinatorial. In grid world it's very
small. In normal problems it's very big.
There's a set of actions you can take.
Um and the difference is instead of um
taking an action in a state resulting in
another state. So before we had the
successor function that took uh a state
and an action and mapped that to a
resulting state s prime. Now instead we
have transitions and rewards which give
a distribution for a given state and
action over the resulting states that
are possible maybe all of them and the
distribution over them that comes in the
form of the transition function which is
tsas prime but you should think about
that as the probability of landing in s
prime if you started in s and chose
action a okay so in grid world you're in
some position s you take some action a
like north and there's a few states you
might land in with probability point 8
and 0.1 and so on and that's the
transition function. The reward is
associated with a transition. You're in
a state that's where you start. Um you
take an action you chose that and then
there's a result that you don't control.
This is non-deterministic. when you
experience this transition SAS prime uh
you receive this reward and that encodes
um that encodes how much of the
incremental reward you receive right at
that moment. There's an important
distinction between the rewards you
receive in that moment that little
living reward the plus one whatever it
is and the entire reward for the whole
game that you played or the episode that
you experienced. So one thing to be very
careful about is the distinction between
instantaneous rewards that happen on a
specific time step and the total utility
which is a sum of rewards maybe with a
discount. Okay? And then some start
state the quantities that we defined and
that we're going to really need to be
clear on today because we're going to be
writing lots of equations about them,
lots of optimality conditions, some
proofs of some properties and a couple
algorithms. Um and it these things are
going to start to blend together. I
promise you there's going to be a lot of
values and policies and Q values and
Bellman equations and they're all going
to look nearly identical because they
are there's a small number of ideas that
can be remixed in lots of different
ways. These algorithms are all just
exercises in remixing these ideas. So be
super super clear on them. So here are
some quantities you need to know about.
A policy is a map from states to
actions. So it's usually written pi and
it takes a state and tells you the
action. Okay, there are probabilistic
policies that map from a state to a
distribution of actions. If you're in
the state, sometimes do this and
sometimes do that. We're not talking
about that. These are deterministic
policies. When you're in a state, there
is a fixed action recommendation. Some
policies are better than others. How do
we talk about that? We can talk about
utilities, which is the sum of
discounted rewards that you receive in
an episode of this game. Um, when we
talk about the utility of a state,
that's called a value. that is the
expected future utility from a state
starting in that state and then
according to some policy perhaps the
optimal policy. So the utility is a sum
of uh discounted rewards. A value is an
expected sum of discounted rewards under
some assumption like optimal play. And
that's the part where you scratch your
head and you're like what is optimal?
How do I put optimal play in an
equation? And the answer is well
recursively actually. Uh and we'll see
that today. There's something new which
is Q values which is something that we
did not have to talk about before but
they're super important and we'll talk
about why that is. The idea is if you
ran an expect from a state you would get
its value. So the value of a state is
put a little star here to say optimal is
the average score you'll get. So average
sum of discounted utilities starting in
that state and playing optimally
whatever that means. The Q value is the
average score you'll get starting from a
Q state which is just a chance node. A Q
state remember is a state action pair.
This is a weird concept. Okay it is I'm
in a state I have chosen an action. the
action has not resolved and of course
the future has yet to happen and it's
the score I will get from here on out
after after I commit to this action. So
this action may be terrible but after
this action I'm going to play optimally.
So it's a bit of an odd thing. I think
it's easiest to just think about it as a
chance node in the tree and it has an
expected max value too. Q value is the
expected max value of a chance node. All
right
here are some optimal things. when you
see stars usually means optimal. And um
here are some quantities that we're
going to have to be able to write down
conditions about. So for example, the
value of a state we just talked about
that is basically what expect max from
the root gives you. So the value of a
state is the expected return under
optimal play which means it is a maximum
over all the actions of the optimal Q
values of the chance nodes below me
which are in turn an average over their
children of their optimal values. And so
this can be computed recursively. We'll
come back to that uh very shortly. So
the value of a state is the expected
utility of starting in that state and
acting optimally. The utility or value
of a Q state SA is the expected utility
starting out having taken action A
already, even if it's bad, right? We
talk about the value of a state. Some
states have bad values. You're in that
state. Maybe you don't want to be in
that state, but we're talking about how
well you'll do if you play optimally
here from here out. You're in a Q state.
Maybe it's not a good Q state. We're
talking about the value if you play
optimally from there out. It's an
important distinction. We write the
optimal policy as pi star. Um which is
it's important to note that um because
these policies recommend one action per
state. The whole policy like you could
have the right action here but a wrong
action somewhere else. The optimal
policy is the one which gives you the
optimal action everywhere. Okay. How do
we define that again recursively? All
right. So let's take a look at what
these look like in grid world. So this
is the visualization from the demo I
showed you last time. These are all the
squares in the grid world. Remember you
can move north,southeast, and west. In
this case, the there's a um 0.9
discount, which means a reward one step
in the future is worth 0.9 of what it
would be if you got it right now. And
10% in the future is 0.9 to the tenth of
what it would be if you got it right
now. And so when you add a sequence of
rewards and there's big rewards but very
far away, the discounted sum will be
small.
This is a an instance where there is
some noise. So the robot might slip and
there's no living reward. So the only
points you get are at the end. And in
this case, you can see that if you're in
this square here, let me switch to a
different color. Um if you're in this
square here, the only action you can
take is exit. It will give you a plus
one right now. And so the value of that
state
is one because the only thing that can
happen is you exit and get one. The
value here is negative one because the
only thing that can happen is you exit
and you get one. For every other state
the value h is going to be a a max of a
sum of you know it has to be uh
recursively computed. So for example
this 085 that value the optimal action
in this case is to move to the right and
sometimes that fails. So we don't always
move to the right. Sometimes we slip to
the south and then we try to move back
north and when we try to move back north
sometimes we succeed and sometimes we
fall into the pit and all of that
averaged together. all the things that
could happen
expect to max together works out to.5
and that should make sense kind of
roughly because we're mostly going to
get this point this 1.0 I know we're
mostly going to get it one step in the
future. So it's going to generally be
worth 0.9 instead. And there's going to
be some slipping involved, some of which
we recover from. And so we're going to
lose a little bit of value to a mix of
getting the one but later, which
discounts it or falling into the pit
with a lower probability, but that's
pretty bad. Okay, so that's all blended
together into this 085. Just want you
have like an intuition about what these
things are. And of course, some states
are good and some states are bad. um
this state here that we were talking
about as the start state in the past,
the expected value is about 0.5 because
by the time you make your way to the um
to the one um mixed in with a tiny
chance of falling into the pit, all of
that kind of blended together gives you
an average score of 0.5.
Q values look like this. Each state and
action has a Q value. So in this case,
the states are split to show the
different actions you can choose.
There's not always a way to visualize Q
values like that, right?
In this case, the actions kind of nicely
line up with the states themselves, but
there could be, you know, there could be
an action that's like uh jump to random
location or like a deploy parachute or
whatever that doesn't have a spatial
place to put it. So, you're going to
think conceptually in every state, I
have a set of actions I can take. Each
one is going to have a Q value. One of
those will always be the value. So if we
look here and we see that 085 the value
085 was backed up by the action east
there are other actions you can take but
even if you take them even if you play
optimally you'll get a lower score and
you can see that here and this is
actually a really important point about
the difference between values and Q
values. Values tell you which states are
good but ultimately like you don't
really have control over that. What you
have control over is your actions. Q
values actually make it really easy to
see and we'll come back to this. It
makes it really easy easy to see which
actions are going to be good ones. All
right, so let's figure out how we
compute these things because now that we
have a sense of what they look like, we
need to know precisely where they come
from because it's very easy to feel like
things are fuzzy here in this unit. So
the general approach is to describe a
set of optimality conditions called the
Bellman equations which describe what
optimal means and they describe what
optimal values mean and optimal policies
and they do that in a mutually recursive
way as equations. These are going to be
conditions. It will be values obey these
equations in the same way that a system
of equations like the solution obeys
those equations but the system of
equation doesn't tell you how to solve
it. These equa the Bellman equations
here are going to characterize the
solutions but they're also going to give
us um algorithms for finding fixed
points which will turn out to be uh like
really close and structured to the
equations themselves. So let's take a
look. So what are the Bellman equations?
It's basically a recursive decomposition
written as an equation. It says in order
to be optimal, step one is you take one
optimal step and then step two is you be
optimal in the future. This is helpful
because this becomes a recursion or a
mutual recursion depending on how you
write it. And you can worry that you
can't solve these equations, but they're
pretty straightforward to write down. So
we can go back to the idea of expect and
the definition of optimal utility to
give a one-step look ahead relationship
between these values. Again, we don't
know what they are, but writing down how
they relate to each other is hopefully
going to eventually give rise to an
algorithm to compute them. So, here's
the first one. This just says what's the
expected max value of the root that is
vstar of some state S. And of course,
this will be true for all states S.
There's a copy of this equation for
every state S. So vst for any s is going
to be the maximum of
its children just like expect well what
are its children? Um its children are q
states and they have optimal values qst
star. So here's the first one. Vstar is
the maximum of array of the q stars
beneath it. Well okay that's the easy
one because we need to know
what is the value of this node. Well,
it's has something to do with all of the
possible successors, but we've committed
to our action A, and we don't know what
S-rime is going to result. We don't know
what transition we're going to
experience. We don't know what reward
we're going to get, but we do know what
the possibilities are and how likely
they are and what the reward will be if
they happen. So, we can take a big
blended average, and it's going to look
like this. So, the value of that chance
node Qstar SA is going to be um an
average, an expectation over all the
possible S primes we could land in.
Okay, so we consider all the S- primes
that are possible. We look at the
probability of ending up in that state
to wait that term in the average. And
then if you ended up in S prime, you
would instantaneously receive the reward
associated with that um with that
transition RSA S prime. You get that
reward right now. You land in S prime
and well presumably you do optimal stuff
after that. What score will that give
you? Well, that's V star. So except now
it's V star of S prime where you landed
and it's discounted by gamma because
everything you do now will be one step
into the future and as we recurse those
gamas will pile up and the discounting
will work the way we said it would. So
this right here is probably the single
most important thing of the lecture that
you understand the pieces of this which
is instantaneous reward plus discounted
future reward
averaged over outcomes of my action.
Okay? Okay. And if you ever forget that,
just remember this uh remember this
picture here because you're in SA. You
ended up in S prime and you received R
of SAS S prime and you knew that that
would happen with a probability TSA S
prime. Okay. All right.
In general, you can think about these as
mutually recursive equations. Sometimes
that's helpful. Or you can think about
it as just an equation that inlines all
that together. It's totally equivalent.
And this says vstar is a function of
vstar one time step in the future. This
will be important for when we do
reinforcement learning is we're relating
vstar at one state with vstar one time
step in the future. And in between is
this one layer of expect. Okay. So vstar
now is a max of a sum of a onestep
reward plus a recursion. Okay. So, this
is something that I really encourage you
to just stare at and stare at and work
through and make sure you're solid on
because you're solid on this, everything
else will seem eventually kind of
obvious. And if you're not solid on
this, everything else is going to be
like a blur of one step look ahead
variations. Okay, these are called the
Bellman equations and they characterize
the optimal value. They're a system of
equations. You might not know how to
solve them, but it should make sense
that whatever the optimal values are,
they should have this property. Okay,
any questions on that?
Okay, first we're going to try to solve
these equations. Um, and the way we're
going to do that is first with an
algorithm called value iteration. We'll
then do a variation on this called
policy iteration. But we're going to
start with value iteration, which is a
little easier to understand. And it is
essentially a dynamic programming
approach to building up successive
approximations to the true values that
we hope and can prove under certain
circumstances will converge to the right
answer. So here's how value iteration
works. The Bellman equations
characterize optimal values. They tell
you and again here's that same equation.
It's going to be the same equation every
time. um they tell you that whatever
these val these optimal values are, the
optimal value of a state
relates to the optimal values of states
one step ahead in the tree. So here's S
and here's S prime. And there's a
relationship between them. Whatever the
optimal values are up here, you get them
if you plug in the optimal values down
here and then work through the expect
max, the max and the the the sum. Okay,
value iteration is a method for
computing them and it looks nearly
identical. It's an easy thing to get
confused about. Um,
so all we really do is replace the
equality with an assignment and um, you
see some subscripts appear. I'm going to
talk through what those are, but the
basic idea is you're going to have a
series of approximations. We want to
know V star of S. However, what we're
going to do instead is we're going to
produce a series of approximations
uh
vk which are each numbers for every
state. They're going to get close to the
optimal values, but at the beginning
they're going to be pretty bad and we're
going to make them better and better and
better. And as K gets larger, these
approximations are going to get better.
Um I'm going to talk about specifically
what they mean. Even though that's not
necessary in order to to understand the
algorithm, I think it makes it easier if
you understand what V sub3 actually is
because then it gets a lot easier to see
why this is correct. It's also easier to
remember the the um the algorithm. So
let's build it up here. Um you can think
of this as a fixed point solution method
to these equations. So we wrote down
some equations. One way to solve systems
of equations in general is to apply some
kind of fixed point operator which takes
a wrong solution and contracts it
towards the correct solution. All right.
The key idea for understanding what
value iteration is computing and how
it's computing it is this idea of a
timelimited value. So far whenever I've
talked about the value of the state
that's the score you're going to get in
an MDP meaning expect the score you're
going to get acting optimally from that
state forever. Right? So remember in the
um example of the race car, you were
supposed to go fast when it was cool and
slow when it was hot so you would never
overheat and you just like the rewards
just kept kind of coming in forever and
maybe there was a discount or maybe
there were infinite rewards and the game
lasted kind of arbitrarily long. A time
limited value says the game is going to
end in three steps in four steps. And we
say a step we mean a reward. So a game
that lasts one step you'll get one more
instantaneous reward. You'll go through
a transition you'll get an RSAS prime
one time. depth two is you'll get two of
them and it reflects a depth limitation
on the search. So let's see what this
would look like. Um
let's define it. V subks is going to be
the optimal value of S. So it's the same
as V star except if the game is just
going to terminate after K time steps.
Okay, what's nice about this is if the
game terminates in K's time steps,
expect a max will in fact solve the game
perfectly. Maybe not not efficiently but
perfectly because the game only goes
down to depth K and then it just ends
and now it's finite and now we can
crunch our way through it even if it's
slow. So we can talk about doing so we
already have an algorithm. Okay, we can
get VK by doing a depth K expectax.
Let's see if we can do better than that.
Um and let's remember why we wouldn't
just do a depth K expectax. Remember um
this is the case of the racing um this
is the case of the the racing car and
this is so if we were looking at the
expect this is the set of futures from
this state where the car is cool and you
can either go fast or slow and if you go
slow you stay cool and if you go fast
you sometimes heat up and so on and
there's this bad state where the game
ends on you but you can avoid it by just
never going fast when the car is warm.
Okay, this is uh this little tree here
where everything just stops after two
layers. This is V2 from that state.
Another state also has a V2. There's
only three states. So three numbers
characterize uh V subk for any K. All
right. And so we can launch this expect
a max and it would crunch. It would take
a max here. It would take an average
here. It would take a max. And when it
gets down here, it would just terminate
because the rewards come here. Like
there's there's plus twos here and
there's plus ones. And we would crunch
all of that together with all the
probabilities with expect max and we
would get some number. And I don't know
what that is like 2.5 or whatever it's
going to be. It's some it's some number.
um and it's going to correspond to um
just terminating the game early. Let me
show you an example of this in the grid
world.
All right.
So here is this is V 0. If you have no
time steps left, you're not going to get
any rewards. If you get zero rewards,
the sum of them will be zero. So every
state has value zero if you consider the
next zero rewards. But what if you
consider the next one reward? What's
going to happen?
Well, if you're only gaining one reward
and you're in this state here, the one
reward you're going to get is a one. So,
this thing should have a value of one in
V1. This one will have a value of
negative one in V1. And a state like
this, what can you do in one step? Well,
you can get to the exit, but you can't
take the exit action. So, in one step,
this thing can only thing it can do is
experience a living reward. So, V1 is
going to be whatever the living reward
is. same for all of the others. And I
think in this one, we're going to find
out in a second, but I think for this
one um I launched it with um living
reward of zero. So, if I do this, you
can see the only states that have
non-zero value are the exits because
they're the only place you can get to a
nonzero reward in one reward. Again,
assuming the living reward is zero. If I
go again and I think about what I can do
in two steps, I'm going to compute V2.
That's the value of each state under
optimal play if the game lasts two
steps. All right. What's new? What's new
is that from this square and this square
only, you can get into the good reward
and exit. So, this one is going to start
to have a positive reward. How about
this one? What can I do in two steps? I
can't make it all the way into the good
exit and take the good reward. I can
wander around and get reward zero. I can
also jump into the pit and get negative
one. So there's things I can do, but the
best of them is the one where I don't
jump into the pit. And so this one is
going to stay zero. This is an important
distinction. This one um here becomes
positive because in the horizon of two
steps, I can take a positive action.
This one has interesting things in the
horizon, but under optimal play, you
don't do them. You just continue to take
zero rewards. Does that make sense?
The reason this is just 72 and not
higher as we saw before is because part
of its full value comes from trying to
get into the exit, slipping, recovering,
and then succeeding.
Those trajectories are longer and they
require more time steps than two to fold
them into the computation. So let's go
to V3. Think about what for from what
squares can I reach something other than
zero? I can reach something other from
zero here because I can go east and east
and out. So this one should become non-
zero from here. Now I can go north and
east and out. This one should become non
zero. These ones I can get into the pit
but I can't do anything better. And this
72 in three steps can I do I have time
to I have time to try to move and slip
and end up where I am in the same place
then move then succeed. So its value
should go up because now there is
another reward. It can get the one where
it gets the one but one step later.
Okay, so let's see what we get there.
All right, so that grew. Are we done?
No, because there's still a bunch of
places where we have nonzero rewards,
but just not yet. Not in V3. What about
in V4 and V5? And you can see that the
reward is both spreading outward because
we're getting more and more places that
can see the horizon that is required to
get the one. We're also seeing
everything grow because there are longer
trajectories that involve slipping and
catching back up that add to it. All
right,
I'm going to keep we're going to do this
again. So, I'm going to keep sort of
running these and you can see they're
eventually going to like
they're going to eventually start
changing less and less and we could call
that converged. You know, we would have
some criterion and so on. All right, so
there's there's the same rewards we had
from before except we calculated them
step by step. Let me run that one again.
Except this time what I want you to wa
watch is I want you to watch the um I
want you to watch the policies and I
haven't told you how to get the policies
out but these are the policies that
correspond to uh to um the increasing
iterations the values right now policy
like it doesn't know everything just
looks equally the same and as we go we
start learning like okay from here I
want to go on uh before here I wanted to
go left but now as the horizon
increases, I want to go north. And then
the these are changing. But if as if if
you watch, you'll see the policy
changes, but not every time. So like
right now, we're in this time where the
policy, okay, one policy just changed
here, but most of the time the numbers
are changing because we're fine-tuning
the values, but the actual optimal
actions isn't changing. So file that
away. Every iteration of value
iteration, the values are are going to
change, you know, slower and slower, but
they're going to change, but the
policies may not. the policies are going
to converge much faster. All right, so
let's take a look at these time limited
values that we were going to compute and
let's turn this into a a couple
different kinds of algorithms. So um
let's start at the bottom. We'd like to
compute
expect values in this way for depth one
trees, depth two trees, depth three
trees. And we'd like to do that in a way
that doesn't like do too much work
because remember each one of these blue
states is the same. They're all
interconnected. So as we go, we'd also
like to cache things. We only want to
calculate V subk for a state once. We
can do that in a couple different ways.
This is the dynamic programming way
where you start at the bottom. So what
you do is you start computing V 0 for
all your states. In this case, we have
three. And then we compute V1, which as
we do those Bellman unrolls is going to
require plugging in V 0, but we've
already computed that. And then we're
going to go we're going to compute V2.
And V2 is going to be a max of a sum of
some stuff plus a V1, which we've
already computed. And then the V3s and
so on. And we'll compute these until we
get to the point where we think it's
good enough. Okay, you should be
thinking about what can I accomplish in
K time steps? And you already know what
you can accomplish in k minus one time
steps. Okay. All right. So here's the
algorithm. You start with v 0 for all
states is zero. And this should be
pretty intuitive because if there's zero
words left, the sum of rewards is going
to be zero. We know it. It's correct.
It's not helpful. But this is obviously
v 0. All right. So now what we want to
do is we imagine we're given vk for some
value of k initially zero. And this is
the recursive step. All right. So we're
given some vector of VK for some K.
We're going to do one ply of expect or a
one-step look ahead and we're going to
do it from every state. So for every
state S, we execute the following. For
every state S, we're going to fill in VK
plus one
for this state S. And what we're going
to do is as follows. We're going to
build this expecttomax search. And we
know as soon as the computation of VK
plus one refers to VK, we're just going
to look it up in our cache because we
already computed that on the last round.
So how do we do the search? The same as
always. We're going to take our root. We
have to take a max over all the actions
because we get to pick and only the one
that gives us the best Q value is going
to actually determine the value. That's
the nonlinear part of this. Then we have
to take the Q value which is an average
over all the outcomes. That's consider
all the actions. Uh sorry, there's a max
over the actions. Then we consider all
the states here. It's a max over all the
actions. It's an average over all the
results. S prime. For each s prime, we
take the instantaneous reward for that
trans transition plus the discounted
cached
vk. So the rewards I can get in k plus
one time steps are the rewards I can get
in one time step plus the rewards in the
remaining k from the recursive call
which we've already computed. All right.
Rinse and repeat. You return repeat that
until convergence. Talk about some
properties. We're going to run an
example. Um and then we're going to
prove that this works. Any questions on
what it is first.
All right. So complexity. Let me lose my
ink here. What's the complexity? We have
to do this for every state s. So there's
going to be a factor of s right here. To
do an iteration of this, you have to
touch every state. All right. For each
state, what do you do? Well, you have to
enumerate all of the actions you take.
There's a for loop over actions and for
each one you have to see whether that's
the best. Okay, we'll come back to that
later but that's a factor of a. And then
for each action you have to consider all
the things that could happen which in
general is another factor of s. Though
if your branching factor were smaller
maybe your actions are non-deterministic
but they can't actually result in
anything. So in grid world you can't end
up anywhere. There's only like three
places you can end up or four places you
can end up. So this this s here in
principle is another factor of s but in
practice it's actually more like a
branching factor. So in general that's
s^ squ a where s is the size of the
state space. One of those s's is really
all of the states. You got to compute v
for all of them. The other one is more
like the branching factor. Okay. So
that's complexity.
There's a theorem that says that under
certain conditions this will converge to
the optimal values and that there are
unique optimal values. We'll prove both
of those at the same time. And um an
idea that you should have in your head
is that as we are approximating these
values, the policies that correspond to
them will converge much faster. You
don't need to know exactly what the
value is to know that this one is better
than that one. Okay? So we'll use that
uh a little bit later.
Okay. Um
if you see this presented elsewhere, you
will often see a version where there is
simply a vector V and these updates are
done in place.
We are not doing that. Every step
creates a new copy of V which it
populates using the old copy of V. That
gives us this way to very crisply say
each vector is the Kstep look ahead
approximation. If you do it in place,
you lose that property.
But the algorithm will actually still
work. So just in case you see that
elsewhere,
let's do an example. Let's compute V 0,
V1, V2. And about halfway through this,
we'll realize why we use computers to do
this. Um in V 0, that's easy. Uh if
there are zero time steps, the total um
the total value left, no, is zero. And
remember this is uh this is the the
racing case where you can go you can go
fast, you can go slow. Going fast always
gives you two points. Going slow always
gives you one point. And it turns out uh
just to make this faster, it turns out
that you should go slow when it's warm
and you should go fast when it's cool.
We worked through this last time. We're
going to assume there's no discount. So
now what do we do when we try to compute
V1? Well,
mechanically we run this update.
We compute V1 and that means we plug in
over here V 0 which is just going to be
zero. And so what that means is for each
state we consider what we can do in one
step. And so let's do an example. If I
am in the state where I am cool, what
are my choices? I can go slow, I'll get
a point. I can go fast, I'll get two
points. And then the game ends. It
doesn't even matter where you go. Um the
game's just going to end then. So we
know that in one step from cool uh from
the cool state, I can get two points by
going fast. If I'm in the red state
here, I can go fast or I can go slow.
But fast just overheats me. And so I
have to go slow. And so I can only get
one point. And if I'm overheated, I'm in
a terminal state. So there's zero more
points I can get. All right. So V1 was
easy because it was just what can I get
on my next turn. V2 is where things get
interesting. So let's do um
advance this and put the ink in. Um so
let's do the computation. Let's do it
from
well um this is always going to stay
zero. Once you're there, you're stuck
there. So let's do it from red. So
what's going on in red? We want to know
VK + one of the of I guess the state is
called warm. We want VK plus one from
warm. That's a max over the actions fast
and slow. One of these is going to give
me my value and the other is going to be
wasted computation because it's going to
not be the maximum. So we kind of have
to compute both to see which one's going
to be the maximum. Um but we can compute
them here
to save time. We know that fast is not
the right action. So I'm just not going
to compute it. We could compute it. It's
expected value be like -10. It wouldn't
be the max. And so we're not going to
I'm not going to do that branch. So
that's the max part. The max is going to
happen um using slow
though as an exercise go compute fast.
You'll see it's not as big. Okay. Okay,
so for slow and now I have to average.
What am I averaging? What are the S
primes? Well, when I do slow here, half
the time I end up in warm
and half the time I end up in co cool.
And so I have to consider both. And each
one happens 50/50.
Now, if I am warm, if I end up in warm
and I go slow, I'll get a 0.1 on that
round. Sorry, I will get a plus one on
that round. And there's no discount. So
the gamma is one. I will get VK which
was V1 which was for the uh the warm
state was one. Okay, that was this if I
end up in the cool state my
instantaneous reward will be one but
then I will get in the future in my one
remaining time step I'll get a two. So
the average of 1 plus 1 and 1 plus 2 2.5
and if you work this one out it's going
to be 3.5.
And we could keep going and we would
accumulate uh better and better
approximations to v subk. Okay, this is
already a lot to work out by hand. So
computers will do this.
Let me stop for a second before I talk
about why this works.
Just remind yourself we are computing a
sequence of vectors vk. Each one
represents what expected max would give
you aka the value if the game lasts k
more steps. as K gets lar larger, we're
talking about more and more of the game,
and
we're hoping this will end up with the
right answer. Well, first of all, how do
we know this is going to converge to the
right thing or for that matter at all?
Because in the racing game, you could
get points forever and you could choose
not to discount them. Well, there's a
couple cases. So one case is that this
MDP actually has a maximum depth like
the structure of the state space is such
remember CSPs only went so deep like so
there are MDPs that only go so deep and
the structure of the state space such
that it has a maximum depth once you get
to that depth M v subm will in fact
represent the uh the expected max value
of infinite depth for all states so easy
okay but usually that doesn't happen so
the other case is what happens s if um
this game can go on forever. And if the
game can go on forever, like the answer
is maybe infinity, right? The only time
that games that go on forever really
have a well- definfined value is when
the discount makes sure that the stuff
that's infinitely far out, you know,
doesn't sort of uh doesn't wreck your
day. And so in this case, if the tree
doesn't have a maximum depth, we have to
assume for this proof here, we have to
assume that the discount exists and is
less than one. So this there's some
gamma less than one that we're
discounting with. All right. Well, in
that case, let's think about um for some
given state S, let's think about the
difference between VK and VK plus one.
They are both equivalent to running
expect on some tree. In this case, the
tree has depth K and in incorporates the
next K rewards. Over here, it's depth K
plus one and incorporates the next K
plus1 rewards. Which means these trees,
their probabilities, the numbers,
everything in this tree is identical
except for that bottom layer.
And I can think about
this one as having one more layer, but
where all the rewards are zero. Does
that make sense? So you got these two
trees. We're doing expect max over. The
one on the left has zero on its bottom
layer. The one on the right is identical
except it's got other stuff. Well, how
different could it possibly be? Well,
the most different this could be is if
all these rewards were as large as they
possibly can be. So, here we have to
make the assumption that these rewards
are bounded. So, there's some rax uh
there's some which is the largest
absolute value any reward can have. All
right, so we've got these nearly
identical trees. One has zeros at the
bottom. The other is actual rewards.
That last layer is at best our max, at
worst our min. Everything is discounted
though. So everything down here when
it's actually added is added in at gamma
to the k and gamma is less than one. So
if I push k out far enough eventually
this just won't be very different
because everything's discounted. These
two values are going to be at most that
discount to the depth times the largest
reward and absolute value. And that
means that as I drive K up, this whole
term because of that exponential decay
is going to get as small as I want to
make it eventually. The more the
discount, the faster, the smaller the
absolute value of the rewards, the
faster, but this will eventually
converge. And we can say something about
how fast it converges. In particular, it
converges exponentially fast in a way
that relates to the the discount. Okay,
so it's a sketch of the proof there.
What did we have to assume? Well, we had
to assume either um finite game or a
discount.
You say, "What happens if it's
infinite?" Well, sometimes the values
are defined and sometimes they aren't,
right? You can have divergent values if
the game can go on forever and you can
get undiscounted rewards forever.
Okay,
that's value iteration.
It's actually fun, I think, to watch the
um it's fun to watch these things
converge over time. Um but I want to
show you something in particular. I want
to go run value iteration again and I
want you to watch like these two squares
which are the only ones where
interesting things really happen, right?
And I want you to watch
how the arrows don't move every at every
turn. So at at the beginning they do. At
the beginning, everything's jumping
around everywhere and information is
kind of flowing out. But if you watch
now, most of the time, most arrows don't
change. Okay, one just changed. Another
one just changed. And now I can keep
iterating
and things aren't changing anymore. And
so what what happened there was that
every iteration the values got a little
bit more precise because we went a
little deeper in the tree. We added like
a contribution from slightly longer
trajectories. Um but
most of the time the policy didn't
change. Every now and then we would have
um we would have the values change
enough that the optimal actions actually
changed. And this is going to bring us
to something called policy methods. I
think here let's take a let's take a one
minute stretch break. Um,
and then we're going to come back and
see if we can use the fact that most of
the time the maxes in value iteration
point to the same actions round after
round after round. We should be able to
make use of that. Okay, so uh, one
minute stretch break and I'll use that
to reset my tablet.
Any
questions while we're stretching?
>> Not sub stretching.
There's no difference if you have a
certain value
like for example dep
yeah so the gamas are convenient when
the discount is steep because all the
algorithms converge really fast but that
really is the same as saying give me
actions which give me rewards now and I
don't even care what happens later in
the game. That may not actually be what
you want. So assigning a gamma that is
steeply discounted is not an approach to
solving the problem. It is a property of
the problem you are solving. So problems
come to you with a gamma. I'm a problem
where what I care about is the sum of
rewards. I'm a problem where I care
about the sum of discounted rewards. You
can't be like, you can't take a problem
that doesn't have a gamma, apply a
gamma, and expect your solution to
qualitatively match what's actually
optimal.
>> It's a good question.
All right, let's talk about policy
methods. Um,
first,
uh, we need to build up some sub
routines that let us compute things
other than the optimal values. I said
there would be a lot of variance of
Belleman equations. That starts now.
We're going to have a lot of equations
that are onestep look aheads but on a
slightly different configuration. So the
first thing we're going to do is have
this idea that somebody comes to you
with a policy. Maybe it's the optimal
policy, maybe it's terrible. Your job is
not to compute the optimal policy or the
optimal values or anything like that.
Your job is to just take the policy
you've been presented with and figure
out how good it is. What does that mean?
It means figure out the value of each
state under that policy. even if that
policy is terrible, you'll just get a
small number. So
what we did with expect max all along
was we talked about optimal actions and
the way that worked is we would kept
finding ourselves in this situation
where we would say all right there's a
bunch of actions A and we're going to
take a max over all of the options A of
these Q states which were all going to
be a sum over all of the states S prime.
Okay,
that max is the part that makes it
optimal. The max here makes it optimal
for one step. And if under here there's
a recursive definition of the value, all
the maxes below are what makes it
optimal in the future. So having maxes
in the
um the action layers gives you a tree
whose values computed recursively will
be the optimal values. But that's if you
take optimal actions. you could instead
just do what pi tells you to do and you
would still get a tree of things that
could happen because the actions don't
suddenly become deterministic. It's just
there's no actions to choose anymore.
You're just looking at this one action
um which is what the policy tells you.
So that whole branching factor of a is
gone in this tree. When you're at a max
node, there's only one thing you do.
It's what the policy tells you. there is
still a sum over the possible outcomes
because there's a bunch of things that
happen and you have to average them
together. So if we fix a policy the tree
is simpler doing expect over it or
anything else is going to be quicker
because every other layer went from
branching factor a to branching factor
one and the question is what do we even
get if we compute min if we compute
expect here but we only use the fixed
thing. Well, now instead of getting the
optimal values, we get the values
according to this policy because we'll
compute the average outcome under this
policy. All right, so let's take a look.
Um, this is another basic operation
computing the utility of a state under a
fixed usually not optimal policy and we
can define that recursively too. So if
we define the value of s not star not
optimally but pi under under whatever
behavior pi recommends we can talk about
the expected average total discounted
rewards starting in s and following pi.
It's a lot of words so we have to write
that down in a recursive way so we can
make it precise. So we get a onestep
look ahead which is going to be a
variant of the bellman equation and we
can just figure out what that is. Okay,
the value of
uh state s under behavior um
specification pi policy pi is going to
be equal to well there's no max over
actions. You're just doing what pi says,
but there's still going to be an average
of the possible s primes. So we still
don't know what s prime we're going to
get. We know we're going to take action
pi of s. So we know we're going to take
action pi of s. And then we don't know
what s prime we're going to end up at.
Once we land in S prime here, we're
going to get an instantaneous reward. R
of S,
pi of S, that's the action we took, and
S prime. So that's the instantaneous
reward.
From S prime, we're going to continue
following pi, which means we're going to
get the rest of the game averaged under
Pi's behavior starting at S prime. All
of that will be discounted because it's
been pushed one step into the future.
and multiple s primes are possible. So
we're going to average over all of them
with their appropriate probabilities.
And wherever I had action before, I now
just plug in pi of s because the action
is now a function of the state rather
than something I have to uh max over.
Okay, let me replace that with some
prettier PowerPoint. So that's the this
is the recursive relation. It's not an
algorithm, but here let me make it an
algorithm.
All right. Now it's an algorithm. So you
change the equality to an assignment.
It's just like value iteration except
now it's computing values under a fixed
policy. Okay. Um
that's it. That's policy evaluation. So
here's an example. You're in this
corridor where there's fire pits on
either side. And one policy says
whatever square you're in, go right.
Okay. Uh,
seems like a bad policy. It's going to
have values. They're going to be bad.
Here's another one which says always go
forward. This is another policy. We can
compute its values. Presumably, all the
numbers will be a lot bigger because
this is a good policy. In fact, this is
probably the optimal policy. Um, here's
what happens when you run these through
and compute their values. In both cases,
every square has a number. They're still
values. But on the left, because it's a
bad policy, all the numbers are really
low because you're always jumping into
the pit. On the right, when you're doing
the best thing there is to do, the
numbers are higher. It turns out the one
on the right is also the optimal policy.
But to know that, we'd have to like
actually do the work and double check
everything and so on and be really
precise about the about um all the
parameters and so on. All right. So, how
do we calculate these under a fixed
policy? Well, the simplest thing is to
just do value iteration on them. All
right. So let's figure out how that will
work. It's just like value iteration.
And it would go like this there. First
we have to figure out what v pi is for k
steps in the future. Meaning we're going
to start with zero steps in the future.
And for all states that's going to be
defined to be zero. Okay,
there's that. Now we need to know what
happens for k + one steps. So we imagine
we already have computed vk under pi for
all states. Just like before with value
iteration. Now we're going to find VK
plus one under pi for some state S.
Well, what's that going to be? Well, now
we think about the expect search that
this represents for one step. We're
going to do a one-step look ahead,
except now there's no action selection.
So, we just are going to do pi of S. And
that means the first thing that happens
that we're not sure about is what S
prime we land in. So, we're going to
take P of S. We're going to land in S
prime. We're going to receive the reward
for S. pi of s prime.
We are then going to recurse and that
will give us v pi for now only k more
time steps starting in the landing state
there's a discount and we have to
average that over all the possible s
primes weighted by their likelihood.
So if you start saying wait a minute I
keep we keep writing this exact same
equation with like minor variations
that's that's that's pretty much it. Um,
so that's the recurrence there and we
compute those and we run that. How is
this different? I guess I should take
that away and ask you first. So what's
different? This is different than value
iteration. What changed?
>> I guess you're just going down one path.
>> Yeah, you're just going down one path.
Okay. And what did we do before? Right.
>> Before we had this like max over a. We
don't have that anymore. Well, what was
that max over a in your code? That was
like a for loop. It was like for all a
in big a recursively find the value of
the the Q state below it. Okay, we just
like lost a for loop over a. That means
the whole thing is going to be faster by
a factor of a. So the more actions you
have, the better this is because instead
of checking them all one at a time at
every single step of every single
update, you just pick the one the policy
tells you. So this is going to be a
factor of a faster. The rest is still
going to be s squ because you still got
to fill this in for every um state. And
in principle s prime could be anywhere.
So this is going to be s squ where again
one of those ses is really s and the
other is like the branching factor which
could be as bad as s. Um but we've saved
a factor of a.
That's great. This a lot faster per
iteration than um value iteration. It
also doesn't compute the same thing. So
it remains to be seen whether that's
useful or not. Um there's there's
actually another way you can solve
these. So um if I go back to these
equations here, like let's just stare at
this for a second. Let's forget this is
AI and there's grid worlds and all that
stuff. Just stare at these equations.
What are the unknowns? Right? The
unknowns are these variables vi of S.
How many unknowns are there? One for
every state.
Any other thoughts about how we might
solve this?
So this is something you've had a tool
for for a long time. Yeah.
>> Yeah. This is just a system of linear
equations, right? As a big matrix like
do whatever you do with systems of
linear equation. It's probably a big
system of equations. But these are just
linear. The thing that was preventing us
from looking at the these optimality
conditions and saying just use your
linear algebra is because the max made
it nonlinear. the max prevented you from
writing this down in a way that was uh
that was going to be um
that was that was going to be compatible
with those tools. But without the maxes,
this is just a linear system. You can
just you can just do whatever you do
with linear systems. Um so policy
evaluation is much faster with the minor
problem that it doesn't actually solve
the right problem. Right? It computes
values under a fixed policy. So you know
you can't have everything. Okay? So
policy evaluation takes a policy and
gives you values.
Let's say I go back to one of well
really any of these here. Let me go
ahead and I'll just pull one up from
here. All right. So if I bring up a grid
world, and it doesn't really matter
which one I bring up.
Um so these grid worlds again, they have
these little arrows in the
visualization. Um
um
ignore those. Pretend those arrows
weren't there. You look at this. What
can you answer from this? Like you can
answer where you'd like to be. You'd
like to be right here and get this one.
But that's not really how MDBs work.
You're in a state. Sorry, you're here.
Too bad. Your job is to pick an action
from here. What action should you pick?
Well, it's easy to look at that and be
like, "Oh, you should pick north." Well,
like, well, maybe. Right. If but
remember that over here sometimes the
right action was you wanted to go north
but you wanted to do it by trying to go
west and failing. So it's actually
really hard to figure out from the
values what you should do. It's just
easy to figure out what state you want
to be in but you don't know what the
best way to get there is that involves
the whole noise model that involves in
general look ahead. And so values don't
tell you what to do. They just tell you
how good your situation is, which is
kind of not really what you need in
order to um in order to act. So policy
extraction is a tool for taking values
and figuring out what policy you should
follow
if those values are in fact optimal.
Okay, so I give you values. What policy
should you follow? All right, so this is
let's imagine somebody hands us optimal
values var they are, right? And the
question is I don't know what should you
do from
what should you do from this state and
the answer is you should go west but
that's like completely not obvious from
the values themselves like there is no
way you can just stare at this and see
that it's that's that you have to
actually do a little expectamax to
figure out based on future states values
what action should take. All right, I'm
in the state. Somebody gave me the
values, but I still need to think
through all my actions and what they do.
And then I can plug in the values that
that I was given. So let's imagine we
have these optimal values and we want to
figure out how to act. It's not at all
obvious. So we need to do one layer of
expect. We need to apply one expect
where we plug in these optimal values as
our truncation function. Okay.
So what we do is you'll never guess what
I'm going to draw here. You're going to
say there's going to be a bunch of
actions. We're going to max over them.
For each one, we're going to need to use
our knowledge of what the transitions do
to consider the landing states. And then
when we land, we're going to plug in
vstar because we've been given that. And
it's awesome. Okay. All right. So, let's
actually write that out. Well, that is
there's going to have to be a bunch of
actions. Normally, we would take the max
over those actions. Then, we would take
an average over their results. T S
prime. And then we need to consider
instantaneous rewards on the next single
step. But in the future, we can just
plug in vstar for the landing state
because somebody gave that to us. So
that's it. That's that same Bellman look
ahead. It's the same um it's the same
little expect a maxax search with like
one minor minor basically notational
difference which is a max takes a bunch
of numbers and tells you which one is
biggest. So a max returns a real number.
This is an argmax instead it's going to
take each of these actions. It's going
to consider the number and it's going to
give you back the action that
corresponded to the biggest number. So
for anybody who's not seen this argmax
notation that's what this means. It's
just like taking the max except instead
of returning the value, you return the
action that gave you the value. That's
it. This is one look ahead against the
values you were given. That has a fancy
name. It's called uh it's called policy
extraction. You're extracting the policy
from the values with a onestep look
ahead.
By the way, not to make it more accurate
in this case, just because you got to do
that to figure out what actions are
right given those values. All right, any
questions on that? That's our last
piece.
Um, this is called policy extraction and
it gives you the policy that the values
imply.
All right,
that sounds a bit like a pain, right?
Somebody gave me an Oracle set of values
and in order to figure out what to do,
I'm still running expect. That's kind of
annoying. And in fact, this is in some
ways like the key thing that held
reinforcement learning back for like
decades was a really important insight
about values versus Q values, which is
that it's really hard to figure out what
to do for values. But Q values actually
make this pretty nice. So let's say
somebody gave me same situation, same
grid where here we're in a pretty good
state, but we got to be careful to bump
up against the wall to not fall into the
pit. and we had to do an expect max to
extract by considering all of the
possible ways I could go and that was a
pain. But let's say instead someone gave
me the Q values. Let's stare at that.
Well, here's that 089
and look, it's associated with the
action west from the optimal Q values. I
don't need to do an expect. I can just
take the action that has the highest Q
value.
Does that make sense? So Q values are
way better even though they're
unintuitive and they're weird and it's a
quantity that's like a hard to wrap your
head around. If somebody's going to give
you oracle values or Q values, you
definitely want the Q values because
action selection is trivial. How do you
act? It's trivial. You just take the arg
max over the Q values. You just like
take the action that has the biggest uh
Q value. And this is not just about
solving MDPs. When we do reinforcement
learning, really the thing that unlocked
reinforcement learning from a place it
was stuck in for a long time was this
idea that you should not learn values,
you should learn Q values. And this came
with not only action selection being
easier, but a completely nonobvious
property about learning optimal values
from nonoptimal behavior. We'll come
back to that um next week, but for now,
much easier to do policy extraction from
Q values. File that away. We'll use it
next week. All right. Um, so here's
policy iteration. We'll run through
this. We have all the ingredients. We're
actually ready to do it really fast. And
then we'll start talking about
reinforcement learning. Um,
okay. So, we actually already did this,
but I'm going to do this here just so I
can go backwards and forwards. Um, so
like here, notice the values are
changing, but the optimal actions are
not. And then there's a change in the
optimal actions. And then here values
are changing the optimal actions are
not. And then again the values change
the optimal actions don't. Values change
and the optimal actions don't. Oh and
then here there's a change in the
optimal action in one place. This is
even when the optimal actions change
they don't change everywhere. So most of
the time you're spending a ton of time
doing this argmax uh doing this max over
all of the actions doing everything size
of a times when the one that's going to
win is almost always the one that won
last time that is slowing you down by a
factor of size of a and in realistic MDP
is a is usually very big. So um in this
case
um in this case we can make things
better. So the problems with value
iteration we're doing these Bellman
updates over and over again. It's slow
and we can see that maybe we can get rid
of this factor of a that would be great.
Um the [clears throat] reason it's slow
has to do with the fact that this max
never changes. And there's actually a
second issue which is pretty important
which is that once you're actually
converging [clears throat] your policy
will converge much faster in general
than your values. So if you're watching
the values and they're changing and
they're changing you're like can I stop?
The answer is probably yeah you can stop
because maybe the policy is not
changing. So maybe convergence we only
have to go until the policy isn't going
to change anymore and these maxes aren't
changing. And so it seems like maybe we
should be able to improve things. Policy
iteration is a solution that combines
all of these ideas into this really
simple alternative approach which goes
like this. Step one,
instead of getting iterating values,
we're going to iterate policy.
Somebody's going to hand you a policy
like always go right and jump into the
pit. Is it going to be the optimal
policy? No. It's probably be a terrible
policy. Somebody gives you a policy
that's like just your starter and you're
going to evaluate it. So you're going to
fix that policy and you're going to run
policy evaluation to calculate that
policy's utilities. So you start with pi
0 and you figure out what the values are
under pi 0 for all states. Pi 0 wasn't
very good. The values are not going to
be very big because you're evaluating a
policy that's not very good. But you'll
converge and you'll converge pretty fast
because this can be done with fixed
actions which means everything's a
factor of a faster. Well then what
happens once this is converged? This is
the trick. You have the actual values
for this probably pretty bad policy. You
now improve the policy. What does that
mean? It means you do one round of
basically value iteration in full. You
do one round of policy extraction off of
these values. So you do a one-step look
ahead where now you allow yourself to
pick new actions. And for this round, we
do check all the actions again to see if
any of them have gotten better. That's
policy improvement. And then you repeat
once you've improved the policy, you
lock it down for a while and you
evaluate that fixed policy which is now
pi 1. So you go from pi 0 to its values
and then from that you extract pi 1
which is a one-step expect with v pi 0
as its truncation function. You evaluate
that to get v of pi 1 and then you
continue this.
So this is called policy iteration.
It's not obvious that it's fast and it's
not obviously that it's optimal, but
it's both. Um, it's optimal because if
all you did was step two and nothing
else, you would actually converge. All
these other steps in between, they don't
hurt you. They just happen to do what
you usually do anyway because the the
max wasn't going to change. any interle
of
um policy evaluation steps and policy
improvement steps will end up being as
long as you kind of as long as you
interle them sufficiently much um and
you do all of them infinitely often
eventually it's it's still going to be
correct. It's still going to be optimal.
Um but this converges much faster
because most of the time all of those
actions you didn't double check weren't
going to change anyway. And so you do a
lot more of the work that you would have
done anyway without wasting time on
computing things that were going to be
dropped out of the max and not
contribute. All right, that's policy
iteration.
Um
uh we actually already talked about all
of this, but here it is in equations. Uh
this is the exact same thing that the um
when you evaluate a policy pi is fixed
onestep look ahead averaged but there is
no action selection here. So you run
this until you're converged enough and
then for improvement you do your onestep
look ahead averaged and you bring that
max back and now you're changing pi i's
to pi i plus ones. So you're spending
most of your time most of your
iterations evaluating and every now and
then you do improvement. Okay, so let me
compare and contrast and let's talk a
little bit about some other stuff.
These comput optimal values in the end.
Even though this one computes a whole
bunch of remember value iteration
computed VK for increasing K. So it
computed optimal values for a truncated
problem. This is computing optimal this
is computing values for a series of
policies which get better and better. So
the thing that's evolving in our main
analysis changes, but it's still going
to be computing optimal values in the
end. In value iteration, every iterate
iteration updates both the values and
the policy. It updates the values
obviously just from its structure. It's
updating the policy every time you go
and you do the max. Every time you
compare all the actions and check which
one's best now, you're essentially
picking the policy of the moment and
you're every time you go back to a
state, you're allowing the policy to
change. um in we don't track that
because we're always reynthesizing it.
For policy iteration, we have to
explicitly track it so that we can
freeze it from round to round. Okay.
All right. They're both dynamic
programs. They both solve MVPs. They
both give you the same thing. They both
put the Bellman equations together and
slight variations and so on. Um here's a
summary. If you want to compute the
optimal values, you can run either one.
Value iteration simpler. It has this
nice interpretation as time limited
values which sometimes you want to
compute anyway. You can do policy
iteration which is often faster. If you
want to compute values for a particular
policy, use policy evaluation. Um and if
you have values that you want to turn
into an the policy they imply, use
policy extraction.
Okay. The standard response from
students at this point is um that all
looks the same. Like we just how many
times did you write T of SAS prime and
average of this and like were they even
different equations? Um
that's right. They're all basically the
same. And once you get to the point
where you look at them and you say, "Oh,
this is just this that's the same thing
but with a fixed policy. That's the same
thing but it's um you know with a time
limit ticking down." That's when you'll
know you understand these and are in a
position to probably talk about
variations of those. It's often a thing
we do on exams. Okay. Um, they all use
these little onestep look ahead
fragments and they only differ in like
fixed policy or max over actions.
Onestep look ahead optimality, whatever.
All right,
any questions on MDP? Because uh we're
going to change the game.
All right,
let's do slot machines. Um, you have a
choice. You can play the slot machine on
the left. Every time you play it, you
get a dollar. That's pretty good. That's
better than real slot machines, right?
Um, you can play the one on the right,
the one on the right, 75% of the time
you get $2 and 25% of the time you get
nothing. Okay, we talked about how money
isn't a utility, but for the moment,
let's just talk about maximizing
expected monetary value. So, we're just
going to talk about none of the none of
the sort of human factor stuff. just
going to talk about which of these has a
better monetary yield. So, I can write
this thing down as an MDP, right? Um,
actually, just to make sure everybody
understands, which one should you play
if you're going to play a bunch?
Sorry, we're all mirrored. Yes, you
should play the red one.
Could we come up with utility functions?
Just to remember back a couple lectures,
if you're only going to play once and
like um you're super hungry and the
sandwich costs a dollar and like maybe
you want to play the the one on the like
we could come up with scenarios where
the utilities don't match up with the
monetary value. We are not doing that
now. We are just talking about what is
the like money maximizing long run thing
to do. Yeah, we should play the red one.
Um how could we write this down as an
MDP? Well, it's a little bit weird to
write down because it's got you kind of
have to write it down formally with two
states in the way we've been talking
about things. Um, where there's a losing
state and a winning state, but they're
actually the same state because you do
the same things from them. It doesn't
matter like there it doesn't matter what
just happened. So, this is a little
little bit weird way to write it down,
but even so, it's a simple uh simple
MDP. Your actions are we can play the
blue machine, we can play the red
machine, and the states are we can win
or lose. Those states are only there
because the rewards depend on the state
you land in. And so we want to have the
winning state so that the arrows that
point into it can give you two on the
red. And so if you look at this um when
you do the blue with probability one,
you win and you get a dollar. So that's
these two arcs. And when you play red,
75% of the time you go to the winning
state with $2. And 25% of the time you
go to the losing state with zero
dollars. And it doesn't and you go to
win or lose and in a way that doesn't
really affect the rest of the game.
Okay. No discount. Let's say 100 time
steps. Both states have the same value.
So let's figure out let's uh let's solve
them. Um remember I give you the MDP.
I've told you all the details. Here's
the states. Here's the transitions.
Here's the discount. There's going to be
a fixed time horizon. Um and so on. We
can compute values. So the value of the
policy um play red. So it doesn't matter
what state you start in. If you just
always play red, your value will be 150
over these 100 time steps, right?
because um twothirds of the time you
threequarters of the time you get 75,
you get $2 and one quart of the time you
get nothing and that's what it averages
out to. If you play blue, you'll get
$100 instead. So play red is the better
policy. If you just had to pick between
these two policies, you'd pick play red.
Okay,
any questions about that
should be like pretty intuitive. You you
know exactly what to do. You don't have
to play here play the game to know this
is the right thing. All right, so let's
play it. All right. Um, which one would
you like to play? Red or blue? Red.
Thank you. Because that's what I
prepared on the slides. You got $2. Now,
what do you want to do? Red. $2. What do
you want to do now? Zero. Uhoh. Should
we start playing blue? No. Let's keep
playing red. Red. Red. Red. Red. Red.
Red. Red. Right. And there's going to be
some variance, but like, you know, you
get it. I told you the odds. You did the
computation. You solved the MDP in your
head. In this case, it was a trivial
MDP. You computed the optimal policy. we
just played it. When we actually play
it, we're not going to get 150 every
hundred
um every hundred runs of the game be
because there is it's non-deterministic.
There's going to be, you know,
probabilities and sampling error and all
of that stuff. Okay, but we knew what
the optimal policy was. Okay, at this
point you're like, where am I going with
this? All right, let's play a harder
game. Okay, here's the harder game.
On the left is a is a the blue bandit
where you win a dollar every time. On
the right is the red bandit where
sometimes you win two and sometimes you
win zero,
but you don't know the probabilities.
All right, so uh the rules changed.
Red's win chance has changed and you
don't know what it is. So let's play.
What do you want to play? What's the
optimal thing?
Red. Okay, let's play red. Got zero. Now
what's the optimal thing?
Red.
You play red forever. Oh, we got two
dollars. Okay. Zero. All right. So, the
point is we can play. If you play blue,
you'll just get a dollar. And I mean,
there's actually a very interesting
theory about the these things in
particular. In particular, playing blue
doesn't give you any information. So,
whether you do it now or later, you'll
get the money at any time. Information
only actually comes in this game when
you play red. And we can talk about that
much later. But for now, the point is it
is not so clear what to do. Which one
should you play? How long should you
play? If it looks like the red isn't as
good, like at what point is it like
obvious enough? When should you give up
on red? Should you give up on it
forever? Like once you give up on it
once, maybe there's no reason to ever go
back to it. Um, and so
this is a much harder setting even
though it's still just the exact same
MTP.
What changed?
What just happened? What happened is you
don't know the rules of the game
anymore. And so when you're playing,
you're not just executing a plan or a
policy that you know to be optimal. You
were learning, right? When you play the
blue uh sorry, when you play the one on
the right um and you play the red,
you're not just getting those rewards,
you're also getting information about
the MDP that you were missing. And that
is different. Okay, that was learning in
particular. That was reinforcement
learning. The formalism that we use for
reinforcement learning here is that
there is an MDP just like there was with
expect and value iteration all that
there's an MDP
but you can't solve it with just
computation because you don't actually
know all the parameters you have to
actually play the game and as the
experiences flow in suddenly you can't
just be averaging stuff together like
you can't just know that it's TSAS prime
you have to do things a bunch of times
to get a sense of the average and
there's always noise and there's always
variation and there's always thinking
about those those quantities. And um
what we just did already brings in the
key ideas in reinforcement learning that
we're going to see intensely next week,
but throughout a bunch of things in the
course. First of all, um there's this
idea of exploration. You've got to try
actions you haven't taken to see what
they do. Okay? So, you needed to play
the red one to see whether it was good
or bad. You just don't know until you
try. Um there's an idea of exploitation.
Eventually you know enough to know the
good stuff from the bad stuff and you
got to start doing the things that bring
you rewards. So you want rewards over
time and there's an inherent trade-off
in reinforcement learning between
exploring which primarily gives you
information and learning and
exploitation which gives you rewards and
how should we think about that trade-off
and actions that blend them. Okay,
explorer versus exploit will come up a
lot. There's this notion of regret,
which is even if you are make good
choices about how to learn, you're not
going to do as well as you would have if
you had known that the red um machine
had a bad payoff, right? There is a gap
between what you could have done and
what actually happened. Even if you're
making good choices, you're still going
to be making mistakes. Sampling is
suddenly um statistics is suddenly
relevant because of chance. You got to
try things over and over. Just because
you get $2 once doesn't mean you're
always going to get it. Just because you
get three zeros in a row doesn't mean
that it's always going to be bad. Once
you've done it a hundred times and never
won, well, maybe you're now starting to
learn something. And how to balance the
statistics against the rewards. And also
difficulty. Like this is a lot harder.
This is about the simplest MDP you could
imagine to the point where you could
just solve the whole thing in your head
with known parameters. And it's very not
obvious when you should stop playing the
red um stop playing the red bandit when
you're actually doing this. So the
difficulty of solving these things has
ratcheted up immensely. Um so next time
we're going to go into reinforcement
learning and the key approach we're
going to take is imagine you're in an
MDP but you don't know what it's but you
don't know its parameters. And in short,
you know your actions, you know your
states, but you don't know the
transition functions, meaning you don't
know what the actions do. Um you uh and
their probabilities and you don't know
the rewards. Okay. So um we'll spend
probably the next two lectures on RL and
then we'll start noticing that really at
the heart of this is the need to be able
to make powerful statements about
probability uncertainty that's going to
require tools we don't have yet. And
we're going to take a step back and talk
about complex inferences and
probability. Okay, so that's next time.
Um thanks everybody. That's it for
today.
All right.
>> Thanks, Zoom.
>> All right, hold on. Sorry.
I hope Zuma's working.